[Music]
hi my name is Kenny pontop and and in
this 2024 release Wave 2 session we're
going to talk about words we're going to
talk about how you can use word as the
layout engine to produce beautiful
documents to send to your
customers a main new feature in the 2024
release Wave 2 is a new word add-in for
document
reports with this you can solve a lot of
things that were not so easy in the in
the normal word layout feature such as
developer com comments that was not
possible and conditional visibility that
was possible but maybe required a few
hacks here and there but not anymore so
let me walk you through it and let's
start by how to install the addin from
the App Store in word all right so here
in word I have at least two different
ways to install the addin I could either
if you have the addin menu here in the
pane you could find the addin menu here
you could also say add ins in the search
bar and go to the get addins action and
the third option is to go choose file
and then choose the get addins action
from this menu let's just pick
that so this is the office addins menu
and here in store I can search for
business Central
Business Central if I do that then I
will find our new add in here and uh I
choose add and then I oh I need to read
the license terms looks good the addin
doesn't have any data it is just a
layout tool so you you're quite safe I
will choose
continue and now I get a new menu in
word called business Central in my
version it states preview in your
version when you watch this recording
there will be no preview it will just be
the the the normal published version so
let's see this addin provides
functionality and command to work with
business Central document reports got it
let's uh see what this thing has so we
get some new layout controls ability to
insert a layout command and then a menu
here if I fold this hide if empty menu
out I get four new actions hide empty
table hide empty table row hide empty
table column and hide field if zero
let's have a look at those but for this
to really be fun we need a a layout to
work with so we'll just go back to
business Central and get
one all right so we're back in business
Central and we need to find the report
layouts page so I will just search for
that
report lay wait a minute oh look we have
also here the new powerp reports uh oh
interesting but that's not for this
session so we'll leave that and down
here under pages and task I have the
report layouts page I will choose that
and this opens all the layouts that are
available now we only want to work with
word in this video um and I need to find
something that that has some good demo
and uh I did prepare a few things so the
report
1303 the draft invoice um have a lot of
of different good demo capabilities you
notice that I added a lot already um so
these are of course not shipped with
your your business
Central so let's uh let's try the first
um feature so here is a layout where I
added some comments I will just export
this so you can kind of see what that
looks like if I
open this layout in
word you can see for this particular
layout that I
added like a comment down here that has
this this hidden comment you can see
that when I hover over it and I also
have here a table where I added some
versioning um for this layout maybe who
did it like when was something changed
who did it what and version and this is
not something we want our customers to
see uh this is just a hidden comment you
can see it's a hidden comment control um
so when I run this hopefully these two
comments will go away but how do I get
them in there if I want to add the table
it's good practice to start with adding
your object like this and then Mark your
table and go to business Central preview
and choose insert layout comment and
this will encapsulate the table with a
hidden comment layout control and
similarly for a text I can just write
something maybe I should
say uh hello world that's a very very
small let's just make that a little bit
bigger hello
world and of course hello world is just
a developer thing so we want to make
sure this is in a comment so I will put
that in in a comment like this okay I
will uh then just save
this and then download it back to
business Central and um when I now run
this layout
here and choose
preview there's no comments the comments
are are not there that's the way it's
supposed to
be the second thing I want to show you
is how you can remove a table if there's
no data in the
repeater let's have a look at a design
here or a layout let me just run that
first so you can see what this means in
this layout I added a new table down
here with some work description and this
is the header and there's no there's no
more lines because there was no data in
this data item so I would actually like
also to get rid of this the header part
of the table and only show the table
when there's data to show so how do you
do that let's go to word take our empty
table and Export that and open it in
word let's just try that
out so here you can see my table it has
the header and a repeater and if I
simply Mark the full table and go to
business Central menu and choose hide if
empty hide temp empty table this
encapsulates the table with a Content or
layout control called hide table if
empty now I save my layout and upload it
back to business Central and if I now
run my empty table fixed layout here if
I run the report with that layout and
preview it voila there's no table
anymore you can use this for the work
description example anything where you
have data that might be conditional on
on what's in the data
set now the next
next couple of demos is more related to
a single data item or a table with data
from a single data item the first thing
is what if you would like to hide a full
Row in that table based on a condition
Let's uh let's have a look at at that so
I have my empty
row layout here and if I just run that
to see why this would be a nice thing it
could be that in this case I would like
to remove line two here based on a
condition on so I only want to show
things with a unit of measure or
whatever you fancy so if one of these
fields in the repeater is empty you want
to hide the full row how can you do that
let's have a look we take our empty row
layout and Export it and open it in
word and uh the way to do this is simply
to to go to the
repeater um and choose which field in
the repeater that controls whether the
row should be shown or not so in this
case the unit of measure is my content
control and if I pick this and go to
business Central and choose hide if
empty hide empty table row and
incapsulate in the repeater this field
so now you can see it this field has a
height table row if empty um layout
control and now I save this and go back
to business Central and upload it so if
we take our empty row fixed
layout and run the report with this and
preview you can now see that the row
where there was an empty unit of measure
has now been prun pruned from the table
in the in the report
the next demo is what if you would like
not to hide a row but hide a
column let's have a look at that so here
I have my empty column layout and if I
run that to show you what it looks like
you can see I just removed the other
table just to make it a little bit more
clear here I have a v identifier that
apparently has
zero uh or no data in here so what I
would actually like to get rid of the
full column a common ask is to remove
the discount column if there's no
discount given so let's uh let's see if
we can uh fix this if I go if I take my
empty column layout and open it in word
here we
go then for the height column you need
to Mark the header in the table in this
case my my label and choose hide if
empty hide empty table column if I Mark
that you can see here in the header then
this will make sure the full column is
is hidden if there's no data so let's
just save this and go back to business
Central and see what it looks like there
so my empty column fixed layout is where
I did this change and if I run the
report now and preview you can see that
there is no column anymore with the vat
the empty one so that has been removed
from the
report the final thing is how how do you
hide a field if the value is
zero so let me show you an example here
run report
preview in this example I have added a
discount column with a zero here and
maybe you just want the Z hero to go
away so uh so how do you do that it
could also be that you format some
financial data and you actually want to
get rid of a lot of zeros so if I take
my layout and open that in word
and let's say I want to take this field
Line
Discount I Mark the full content control
for the data go to our business Central
addin here and choose height if empty
height field if empty if zero sorry now
it's encapsulating the field it doesn't
have to be in the repeater you can also
use this layout control on on the other
part of the layout I close uh save my
layout uploaded to business Central and
if we now run hide field if zero here
you can see that
this removes the Zero from the discount
now a fun fact you can combine the
height field if zero with the height
column so in case you have columns where
there's either no data or there are
zeros and you want to use that you can
remove the zeros with a height if zero
on the field and then use uh hide column
once there's no data in the column
anymore in business Central 2024 release
Wave
2 if you have reports
that use the word merge data item
property to iterate over some things
let's say you want to create multiple
invoices and you want to iterate over
those in the past you couldn't use word
sections in these layouts but now you
can and with that this completely
changed the game for a lot of things
that are tied to the section in word for
instance you you can change margins
orientation columns watermarks header
Footers in the design in the layout and
just bind them to the section want to
see it let's check
out all right let's go to business
Central and open our favorite page
report layout especially if we work with
layouts re layouts let's have a look
report layouts here we go now I have to
know that the
invoice um the invoice report is one of
these that iterate over um things with
the with this property so let's let's
just
find in sales
invoice let's find that okay let's just
try the blue word layout here for real
quick and just pick tray research
and
preview our
report right as you can see we have 51
Pages all P one page each let's let's
try to change these a bit so I will take
the blue layout I will export it and
open it in word and I would would like
to add to this paragraph marker because
this actually helps me see what's going
on so you can see in the end of this
report let me just zoom in a little
bit I'm ending the layout with a new
line and if I here choose layout and
choose breaks I can put in a section
break and I would actually like just to
have a section break for the next
page okay you can see there's a section
break here and
what this means is I'm actually able now
to change things like maybe margins I
want to have a narrow margin and I want
the orientation to be
landscape but these are bound to the
section not to the full document I could
put in more of these properties but you
get the point so if I put something like
uh
landcape here and imagine you had part
of the layout that need a landscape
maybe a table that needs more like be
more wide okay I will uh just save my
report layout here and uh close word go
back to business Central and create a
new report layout based on what I just
did so I'll just do
landcape demo and choose word and upload
the thing I just edited so open here and
there we go because I need to do my 1306
filter let me just find that here filter
by layout
1306 to find all these layouts you can
see and now have my landscape demo and
if I run that
report and I need probably need to pick
tray again and preview let's see the new
design you can see I did put an extra
page in so now have 102 pages but this
but page number two is landscape and
have changed things according to my
layout so this is the way you can now
have much more control over your layouts
using word sections
if you want to learn more about how to
do this let's go to the developer
documentation I'll quickly show you
where you can learn more so here I'm in
the developer docs as always you go to
the AKA link that I show here if I
search for section and word let's just
have a
look the first hit is creating a word
layout good and now I want to see how to
lay out my uh in in Word and let's see
if I can find using sections here we go
so this tells you everything that is
possible with uh with sections also in
previous versions this version of the
documentation has a warning about word
word merge data item for from the past
this is no longer the case in 2024
release Wave 2 so try it out looking
forward to see what awesome things you
come up
with themeable report what's that
imagine you have a customer or you are a
customer and you have your the layouts
for your outgoing documents and they're
all
blue but you're not a blue person you're
a green person so you would like to
change the look and
field and you also just want this very
easy in word and in many other Office
Products there's something called themes
and with themeable reports in business
Central 2024 release Wave 2 you can now
do exactly that take any of these
themeable layouts download them change
the office theme and upload them and now
you're back in business with a different
looking field let me show you how so
here I am in business Central and I have
opened the report layout page and if I
search for
themable layouts you can see the layout
names here with themeable in the title
are all uh all Support Office themes so
let me pick the sales quote and uh let's
just run that for a sec here preview oh
I need a filter sell to customer tray
preview and here we have the sales quote
it's nice and and in this case red but I
don't want red I want green so how do I
do that I
export the layout
to uh to my laptop I open this in word
here we go when I enable editing I just
just need to do one thing under
design and themes I can now pick any
layout or any theme I like here is a
dark blue one here's a green one a
Berlin but I think I want the organic so
I'll pick organic and you see all fonts
and colors both for the title and for
the table change with this I save my
layout and now I go back to business
Central where I create a new layout
based on what I did I'll call this green
layout probably give me give it a better
name and a good description I will
choose word for the format option and
choose okay I will choose the word add
in or layout I just created here and
just upload
that and now this is just
a um cheating me here I put a filter on
themeable and since I called this green
I'll just get rid of that and see on the
sales quote I now have my green layout
here and uh when I run that report and
preview I should pick the sell to
customer tray preview you voila now you
have your layout in the color that you
chose so that's themeable layouts for
you in case you want to try and change
your own layout to make them themeable
this is what you do let me just show you
real
quick right so the developer
documentation is always
aka.ms
slbc developer and if I just search for
maybe just search for theme let's see
what
happens there's one here creating a word
layout I should probably have word theme
but it's the third link here creating a
word layout report and if I choose how
to lay out your report with word there's
a lot of different design uh advice and
the last one here using Office document
themes and if you follow this
instruction for your own layouts in Word
uh you'll be able to make your office um
or a word layout themeable as
well this part is maybe a bit silly but
I call it all the little things we did
to make word layout easier I'm just
going to mention three things we fixed
the word alignment bu and now you can
use funds if you have barcodes for uh
for postal and and then of course the
new office Aptos font I was going to
show you a demo of the word alignment Bo
and how it got fixed but hey it was
fixed in my word so I can't show you the
old version anymore but basically this
bug in word has
been a pain for some time because
whenever you downloaded a word
layout word
would change all the alignment in your
repeaters um to whatever they were but
not anymore so it just works as you
would expect Ed in in word so that's
it for postal uh so we added if you need
barcodes especially for the US I guess
uh we added Planet PostNet and IMB funds
to the business Central service so that
you can now use these in document
layouts and uh and have these barcodes
that can encode an
address and speaking of fonts office has
added a new font as default called Aptos
I really like it I think it's beautiful
and we'll make sure that these fonts are
also available in the business Central
service by October so when you watch
this you'll be able to use Aptos in your
document
layouts all right that's it good stuff a
we uh we now have lots of new things we
could do in word and if you're
interested in other things with layout
check that video that we also did on on
General layout uh capabilities thank you